Okay. Uh we're going to start back with
uh the new book by Gibson uh Song of My
Spiritual Life. And
um we're ready to start the actual text.
Uh so that book, that poem where Sonappa
describes his own spiritual life maybe
for the only time in his he he wrote
like 20,000 pages. this is the only time
he talked about himself and uh
so in that book uh there's poetry he
wrote in
poetry and we have an explanation by
another teacher his name is
se
lama okay ch lama draed yeah shed uh he
lived about 350 years ago okay and
Um so each each major monastery has
their own gishi course and each major
monastery has in my time
uh about
50 advanced gishi candidates. Out of
those maybe four or six will get their
gish. And um
so during that time we studied tech
special textbooks that were written by
uh great llamas of our
monastery and Chon Lama wrote the
important textbooks for my Gishi course
about 3 400 years ago and he was
a his writing is very very unusual and
it's very very extremely clear and
extremely organized and uh very very
deep. Uh he wrote the best commentary to
the diamond cutter
sutra in I we have three great
commentaries. We have
Kamalashila who lived uh 1,200 years ago
and then we have a short one by Basu
Bandu uh or a SAR uh from 2,000 years
ago very short and then we have Chon
Lama's commentary and uh when I had to
choose which one to
use yeah I chose Chon Lama because it's
more clear and so he's amazing And I
checked his life story and
um I I did a biography of him. I forget
which book it's in, but there's one uh
part of his life that I remember a lot.
And uh he had a
dream that he was flying through the sky
uh to the
west to teach to teach the dharma. you
know this is like 400 years ago
something you know he had this dream and
he he himself didn't know why and he he
wrote it in his biography but he said I
don't know what it means I think it
means that his books would come to the
mix
knots and and he would uh become famous
we use his books a lot and they're
amazing they're just amazing and we
found his books they were lost
Uh they were destroyed uh during a war
and we found we found them. Uh it took a
long time. It took Mr. John where is Mr.
John? Took us a long time to I don't
know if you remember Jason went to
Yeah. We sent a guy in in a bus to the
mountains
in in middle of China. He
survived and we he brought back the
copies. So we have them, we input them
and uh this is one of Gibson's book is
one of those books. Okay, it's one of
the books that John saved and it's a
great great commentary to Sonapa's own
life. So at the beginning of
every
Buddhist thing you do, important thing
you do, you bow down to your teacher,
you know, you remember your teacher, you
know. So my teacher mainly Ken Ripache
here and
uh you think about your teacher and you
bow down to your teacher. Uh I also have
a diamond weight teacher. That's another
story.
Uh so Sumati Kerti uh is whose
name? Sonapa's name? Okay. Sum Mati. So
at the at the beginning of Gibson's
book, Chony Lama bows down to Sumati
Kerti. He asks for the blessing of
Sumatiki. But it means uh loanpa. It
means he's bowing. He's asking sonapa
for help and for inspiration. And if
you're going to do diamond way,
uh you got to keep your eyes out for a
diamond way teacher. Okay. Uh and in the
monastery there's an
interesting distinction. Uh we have
Pakan, we have Ken Genan, we have Tawe
Lama. Okay. We have different teachers.
N Lama, we have at least four. Okay. One
is pet again
[Music]
means me
too. Yeah, I didn't get lunch
either. Peter means I did get lunch and
uh Pet means your book teacher who
teaches you the great books. And then uh
Conen Gargan is like
[Music]
your it's more like
uh your
babysitter. Like when you show up at the
monastery, you're seven years old or
something. You want to go home, you miss
your mom, and then they they have a very
sweet,
gentle, cool llama who takes care of
you. And then after six months, you
don't want to go home anymore. And that
was Gishi Barar. That was his job. Uh he
was a content guy then. And then you
have uh Saw Lama. You have your own
teacher. Okay. And then you have your uh
Dor Dor Dean. Dorjan means diamond
captain. And that's your diamond weight
teacher. Okay. And uh so you you have
different teachers. I have 12 major
teachers in the monastery and
um uh but I have one heart teacher.
Okay. And uh
so anyway before you start a new project
like diamond way teachings diamond way
study you got to think of your teacher
you have to think about your teacher
connect to your teacher in your heart.
Okay. And uh and you got to look for
your heart teacher. And what I mean to
say is in the gish
course that may not be your main
teacher. You see your diamond weight
teacher may be somebody else. It may not
be the person who teaches you debating
or the person who teaches you philosophy
or something like that. And I think
uh in in my life it has not been a monk.
My my diver teacher is not a monk. And
uh you know you you will find someone in
your life who's your diamond weight
teacher. I'm happy to be your diamond
weight teacher. I don't have to be your
diamond teacher. You you who you connect
with the most uh is your heart teacher.
I asked my teacher for the definition of
a heart
teacher, my scripture teacher. Uh and he
said the one that helped you the most in
your life. Then I'm like, well that's
another
story. You know, the one who really
helped me to become a good person,
change me, that's a different story.
That might not be the person who taught
me perfection or wisdom or something
like that. So
uh here they bow. The first thing they
do is to remember their root lama, their
heart teacher. Okay? And it could be
anyone in your life. Okay? And don't
rush it, okay? You don't have to say,
"Oh, guess I talked about Rud Lama. I
got to find one before
[Applause]
tomorrow. So, take your time and you
know, they might be sitting next to you
and you don't know it." Uh, or they
might be a thousand miles away and you
don't know it. Okay? So, they will come.
So, don't worry about it. But there will
be there will be someone in your life
who changes your life. Okay? All right.
He bows down to who's
he? Tony Lama bows down to sonapa. Okay.
He felt this connection with sonapa.
Okay. Right. Sumati ki. Sumati means
good mind. Right.
Lo and uh ki means famous but ki means
famous. It's not like uh what's his
name? Brad pit. Okay. Uh that's called
temporary famous. Uh famous
means the ideas you teach spread through
the world. Okay? The ideas that you
teach spread spread through the whole
world. Okay? And you help people
throughout the whole world. Something
like that. That's famous in in
Buddhism. What's the most What's the
normal example of famous for in
Buddhism?
Yeah. The moon or the sun. That's real
famous, you know. That's not newspaper
famous for two days or something.
Okay. All
right. First picture, you
guys.
Nah. Now, I got to teach you guys. I put
numbers on the on the pictures.
Good. Okay. Uh this one is
[Music]
uh there's a tradition when you say your
teacher's name, you know, you say my
beloved, sexy, beautiful, you know,
teacher
Kiri or some, you know, like you don't
just say, "Oh, yeah, my teacher's Kiri."
You know, you you
traditionally
you you don't say their name uh without
thinking of how you feel about them.
Traditionally, you never use your
teacher's
name without pausing and thinking how
how do you feel about them? What did
they do for you? You know, how did they
help you? My teacher gave me my whole
life. So I I don't say their name very
often and I don't say it you know I
don't just say oh you know okay so it's
tradition to
uh speak it uh
only with great purpose or great reason
okay that's a tradition in the diamond
[Music]
way then I thought uh you know if the
world is all name
only which means what $100 question
you don't get. You're the money giver,
not the money
giver. Okay. Mindonly principle. A knife
cannot cut
itself. A person cannot ride on their
own
back. Rob cannot pay himself.
What was the question?
Huh?
No, it wasn't done.
What is the meaning of name? No. Oh,
when I say uh that something's created
by names, what does it mean? It's an
easy
$100. Raise your hand.
You know the the bribe system from
Robin? He gets 50%. He
No. Bento picture. Yeah. Good. Okay.
Fit. Honey.
Yeah. They say say ming.
They say mingham. Mingam means
everything is just names. Uh then it
used to confuse me for many years. I'm
like names only. I I don't understand.
Everything is names. I'm supposed to
understand that everything is names.
It's not everything is names.
Margarita
pizza. It's just the name.
Water. I
mean, don't tell my wife I had a
margarita pizza. I didn't. I had water.
Then it used to confuse me to say
everything is name only. Okay. And it
doesn't mean name only. It means
everything is a picture coming out of
your mind. Okay.
Then I always, it's always funny because
I have I teach these
classes. I teach that everything's
coming from you. I teach the pen, the
pen, the
pen. And then you know the famous story.
Where is Jenny Wong? The famous story
from Singapore Union Trade Convention
Center, UTC. I remember it's a hundred
years
ago. Two things happened. Do you
remember one that that auditorium is is
shaped like this? The the seats go like
this. So I can see in the middle of the
audience I can see the audience right in
front of me. And there's one guy sitting
there
like you know and I'm like
h and he has a scene. So uh during the
break she I said Jenny come here. You
know, she's like, "What?" I said, "You
see that guy with the big eyes? You
know, go get him. He's going to help
you." She's like, "You
sure?" That was
Sugen.
Uh, that was the first guy I remember.
Okay. The second guy I remember there's
a guy I took Q&A and he raised his hand.
And he says, "I have a question, you
know." And he's like, "Um, yes." He
says, "You know, we have to pay to come
to this talk." I'm like, "I don't know.
I I guess." And he said, "Well, I pay
and I came here several years." And I
said, "Okay." And then he said, "And you
teach the same stupid thing every year."
I said, "What did I teach same stupid
thing every year?"
He said, "You teach
that pen thing every year, you know, and
I pay money every year, different
money for the same pen story, you know,
and I I said, "Well, I'm so sorry, you
know, uh, next time I'll try to think of
something different, you know."
Actually, uh, my teacher told me, "You
have to hear it 5,000 times uh before
you understand it, you know." So, you
guys are up to 4,000 or something like
that. And uh I remember this and
then Jenny ran up to me after the talk.
She said, "He's not from our group."
I'm He's from a I'm not going to say the
country. It was another
country. I'll give you a clue. It's in
Europe. I'll give you another clue.
It's where John Brady takes his group
without me.
[Music]
And there's lots of uh what do you call
those things?
No, the thing with the Nutella crepes
with
Nutella.
Understand
we
Okay. All right. So anyway
uh everything is names and all I what I
want to say in diamond way language.
Okay if you force me to teach a diamond
ray
course. Uh all names have deeper
meaning. Okay the name that you were
given as a child has deeper meaning.
Okay. And in diamond way diamond way uh
you have to think about it. Okay. It's
what you know you can do a people want
to tantric meditation involving chickens
or
sex. Uh so I I have one for you. Uh
meditate on your name. You know meditate
on the name that you were given as a
child in whatever language it was and it
has deeper meaning there. According to
Diamond
Way, your parents are very possibly
tantric
angels. Uh if you're here out of 8
billion people, then your parents were
whether you like your parents or not and
whether you're still talking or not, uh
something special there. And there was a
special decision made uh when they chose
your name. Names are not accidents.
And in
Majimika, names create the world. In
Diamond Way, names have a message. And
we just finished a program at Den Huang
IR. And uh we had a wonderful program.
And they're learning how to do deep
retreat, business retreat, and they I
said, "Watch out for messages, you
know." And we had actually uh two
classes. We had several hours of uh
instruction how to how to receive a
message, how to recognize a message.
Okay? And that's a big part of Diamond
Way. Okay? If you want to study Diamond
Way,
uh we'll start talking about the idea
that Diamond Way special beings are
angels are sending you messages. Okay?
And you the the they have an expression
in English. You ready? Did you talk to
the guy? Yeah. Did you tell him what he
was supposed to hear? Yeah. What
happened? What's that mean? He didn't
get it at all. You know, it went over
his head. We say it went over his head.
You know, that's what happened to me.
Um, no. It means uh in the diamond way
uh diamond way special beings. They're
trying to send you messages all day. And
we
just, you know, it just goes over, you
know. They said, "I don't know. Sug said
something strange to me. What?" He said,
"How's your pizza?" I don't know what
he's talking about. You know, when you
don't know what someone's talking about,
either the person's crazy or there's a
message. Okay? You have to decide which
one. All right? So, be open in the
diamond way. Be open for messages. The
first message you ever got was your
name. Okay? The name that you were given
as a
child has mean has special meaning. If
you're here in this
room out of 8 billion people, you are
special. And I statistically you're
special. I'm not trying to convince you
you're special. Okay?
Statistically, if I don't know, do the
percentages. Out of eight billion
people, there's only the ones in this
class listening right now. Okay? Then
you are special. and and the name you
got as a child is special. There's some
meaning to it and you have to it's like
a homework assignment. Okay, if you're
like bored in your cabin and you're
tired of meditating about
dinner, you could meditate on why what
does my name mean? What's it mean
really? Why was I given that name? What
am I supposed to do with that name?
That's a tantric practice. Okay. All
right. It's not in the 18
courses. All
[Music]
right, next
one. Next picture, you guys. Yeah,
Buddha has a plan for you. Okay, I
like my AI is is kind of artificial
idiot. I mean, intelligence. And
uh but sometimes he makes a cool
picture, you know, and I said, I want to
see the
Buddha finalizing some architectural
plans. And he did it. This is the first
try and uh I was really impressed, you
know.
Uh so anyway
uh in especially in Diamond Wayne by the
way Chon Lama bows down to Lord Buddha.
Okay. Uh at the beginning of the book
and to tell you the
truth in the philosophy classes in the
gish
course the the teacher will often skip
these prostrations just oh it's just
usual prostrations they'll go to the
philosophy. I think that's a mistake. I
think you got to look at the pro why who
is chon lama bowing down to at the
beginning of his book. By the way, every
Buddhist book is supposed to start with
bowing down to your teacher. Every
Buddhist book in history is supposed to
start with bowing down to your teacher.
Then for $100, the more experienced
students are going to tell me what's the
next step in every single book by
raising their hand.
promise to compose the work. Good. 100
bucks. Yay.
Yeah. Then they make a promise that they
will write the book. Okay.
Uh sombar damawa. Sayar
damawa.
Sombar. Damcha. Yeah. And make they make
a promise to write the book. First they
bow down for good luck. They bow down to
their teacher and they recognize their
teacher. So, it's a tradition to bow
down to Lord Buddha. And uh I'm going to
teach it from a Diamond Way point of
view. Maybe Gishla's tricking you by
saying you have to pass Lim before he
starts Diamond
Way. Maybe he finished Diamond Way by
the time he finished the
[Music]
Lim. Okay. From a Diamond Way, by the
way. No, it's not exactly I'm going to
keep going, don't worry. Uh but from a
diamond way point of view
uh when you we were in Dunwang we were
reading the diamond cutter we're talking
about the diamond cutter sutra which was
found there in that cave and by the way
the the
finding of the diamond cutter sutra in
those caves affected the town. the town
is infected. Like you can't sit there
without feeling it, you know. And we
went to the shop. We went to the
downtown. We went to a coffee shop. We
went and got chased by hotel owners
because it's not tourist season
yet. And uh you know, and I don't care.
The whole place feels like magic. the
whole town, the whole city feels like
magic because of the book, because of
the diamond cutter sutra, you know. Uh,
and uh, they only found one scroll out
of the whole thing, maybe 50 scrolls,
and only one scroll survived. I think
it's the one with the date on it, but it
also has a beautiful carving of Lord
Buddha on it. And uh, so it here's a a
message. Here's a message from Lord
Buddha. Try to understand this from a
diamond way point of view. When Lord
Buddha taught the Diamond Cutter Sutra,
he saw you studying Chonin Lama at
Diamond Mountain in
2025. Okay. When he taught the Diamond
Cutter Sutra to I don't know 20 people,
30 people. I went there. I sat there
where he taught it. This the seat's
still there. Uh after 2 and a half
thousand years, the stone is still
there. You can sit there. It's fun. Uh I
sat there and uh you know he taught to
2530 people. I don't know. But he was
teaching directly to us at that time.
You understand? He
was we were not less visible to him than
the people sitting in front of him. You
understand? That's what the word Buddha
means. Was he Buddha? Yes. Do you know
what Buddha means? I don't know. It
means sees all things. So when he's
looking at his students 2,500 years
ago, you know, and somebody's there's
some sutra called Diamond
Sutra. He saw you in front of him as
much as he saw those people in front of
him. You see what I mean? He's watching
us right now in the diamond way. You you
have to remember that you you know this
book was made for you. These diamond
cutter
sutra first talk about the diamond
cutter sutra was delivered
to us you okay that dunang scroll why
the one survive with the picture on it
of Buddha teaching I don't
know maybe something special you know he
he was watching this class Buddha was
watching this class when he taught the
diamond kara sutra You understand? And
he was watching you. Okay, that's what
the word Buddha means. Okay, you say, "I
don't know if Buddha can do that." He
can because that's his
name. Okay, Buddh comes from Okay, $100.
Ridiculous bet. You ready? I'm in a mood
today.
Yeah. What's the Sanskrit ultimate
Sanskrit root for Buddha? And what's the
English word that comes from
it? Uh, the most common English
word, huh? Yeah. Video. Okay. Video
comes from
Buddh. Okay. Buddha means the guy who
watches videos all
day. Ser, I'm not kidding. You think I'm
kidding? That's what Buddha means. Okay.
Buddha means now Stanley's a genius. I
told
you he's a Buddha. No. Uh the video he's
watching is us. Okay. So in the diamond
way, you have to remember that. And I'm
going to teach you a special secret
diamond way meditation. Only Gishi
Michael knows about it. Okay? And so I
worked for 19 long hard years in
Manhattan and uh I built a company from
zero to quarter billion dollars. Warren
Buffett bought it and uh it took hard
hard 19 years 4hour on the bus every
day. Okay. Uh and then uh it was hard
sometimes it's hard you know and just
getting people to work together. But
what I realized, I'm vice president,
right? My only job is to keep people
from fighting with each other. That's
all. If I can get the managers to work
together, I can go home, you know.
Seriously, I I realized I got paid
extremely high
salary just to get people to work
together. Uh, and that was my job. I
mean, I I had a title, but it it was
vice president of
uh diamond operations or something. I
have to find the diamonds. That's what I
did to find you guys. Uh so anyway, uh a
hard days, many, many hard days. Many
hard-headed executives to, you know,
workers are easy. You say, "Shut up and
do your job." You tell it to a vice
president to quit. So I'm like uh I get
all these guys I I'm doing and some days
it's just so tiring and I'm so tiring
and I'm so you know overwhelmed. I need
some
help, you know. So I built the building.
We we went there 12tory. I built the
inside. I designed most of it and uh
because it's high security there has to
be there's millions of dollars of
diamonds sitting on the table in every
room and all the rooms are
separated with special electronic stuff
and cameras and all this stuff. So I you
know it was hard and I I built special
bathrooms. Okay.
Why? All the men's toilets are in a
stall also, just like a lady's bathroom.
You
understand? Usually in America, the men
have to pee be standing next to each
other, which is always kind of weird,
you know? And
uh so I built all the bathrooms with uh
separate stalls, you know, and they're
like, "Gisha, no, that's a a men's
bathroom." And I'm like, "I know. I
don't care. Everyone gets a stall, man
or woman, you know. Then why I have a
meditation I do in the
stall. Okay. When it's a hard day, when
I'm having a really hard day and I'm
trying to get these managers to work
together, I'm like, I just go sit on the
toilet without raising the lid. Okay,
it's a special meditation time.
And I'll tell you something cool. You
can be we had vice president meetings
like eight hour
meetings. You know, everybody wants to
get out of there. No one's listening to
anybody. And if you say, "I have a
client coming. He's a billion-dollar
client. I got to leave." They say,
"Stay." Then I figured out if you say,
"I got to poop really bad." They're
like,
"Go, you know, so because you know,
something happens if you stay." And uh
so they're like, "Go." So I go to the my
toilet that I designed. I lock the door.
I don't open the seat. I just sit down
on it and I do a I call it talking to
the Buddha. Okay? I call it talking to
the Buddha. It's a diamond way
meditation. I'm teaching you special
stuff. Okay. You wanted special stuff,
you're getting it. Okay. I don't teach
this to normal
people. Does that make me abnormal? No.
Okay. Um, so anyway, then you sit down
and you talk to the Buddha. Okay. It has
to be loud enough to hear. Okay. It
can't be mental. That doesn't count. Can
the Buddha hear you if you talk to them
mentally? Of course. But if you say
something that you can hear, it's more
powerful. It makes seeds in your mind.
Okay? Are guess now I'm getting seeds.
I'm thinking those thoughts. Doesn't
matter. When you say something, it's
more
powerful.
Okay?
Becomes it becomes a special kind of
karma.
Okay? So you have to talk. They say loud
enough that uh somebody sitting next to
you could hear but not so loud that the
next stall can hear you. Okay. So that's
how loud. Then you you talk to Buddha
and you say Buddha, you know, I'm I'm
having a hard day today. What? Oh, you
know, I got I'm supposed to be patient.
these guys are coming from me, but they
they just don't get along with each
other and it's like the 10th time I
talked to them and I'm just getting
tired and you know, help me out here.
Okay, you can do that. Okay, that's not
a diamond way meditation. That's a stall
meditation. Got it. Okay, wait. You're
supposed to say but you said it would be
a diamond ring man. I'm getting there.
Now you want a real diamond weight
meditation. Same stall, same seat. Gets
a little hard after 10 minutes. I'm
talking. You didn't lift up the
Yeah. And then you say, um, I'm having a
special hard day today, you know, and I
have big big project. I need blessing of
of a special Buddha, you know. I need a
I don't want a regular Buddha. I want a
special Buddha. Today's a special I got
a special project I'm doing. So, uh I'm
going to try to bring all these
executives together and work together.
And I I need big help today. And
Buddha's like,
"Okay, then how do you do that
meditation?" You meditate to Buddha
Mike. Buddha
Mike.
Yeah. Yeah. You will be a Buddha. All
beings have a tatagata garba. All beings
have a seed to become a Buddha. Your
emptiness is your
eligibility to become a Buddha. Your
emptiness is is your if you have
emptiness, you can become a Buddha.
That's called Buddha nature. Okay? You
have it. Everybody has
it. Therefore, you will become a Buddha.
Therefore, you
can talk to future Buddha. They don't
care you existed 10 zillion years ago,
which is how long it's going to take
some people to get
there. Okay? Understand? And it feels
weird, right? By the way, diamond way,
you asked for diamond way. I'm giving
you diamond way. Don't look at me like
that.
Uh, Diamond Way is unusual. Diamond Way
is special. By the way, it's
uh it's incontrovertible. You cannot
debate with me that it's not true. It's
logical. If if it's possible to become a
being who sees all things, which is what
the word Buddha means, then it's not
crazy to talk to your future Buddha.
Okay? If you're not already a Buddha, I
don't know if you are or not. Okay?
Right? I can't
say you are and I can't say you're not.
Uh but I can say for sure either now or
in the future you will be a Buddha. So
it and I can say for sure that either
now or in the future you can hear every
word you ever said in all your
lifetimes.
That means you can ask for help sitting
on the special stall toilet as long as
you don't talk too
loud from yourself as a Buddha. And
that's a diamond way meditation. You
want a diamond way meditation? Now you
got
one. Next Saturday, Tim's going to film
the meditation in the toilet and I'm
going to sit on the toilet and talk to
Michael Buddha, you know. Okay.
Look, I'm a very experienced teacher. I
don't if I don't get a warm seat, I
don't think I can talk,
right? Okay. No, I'm serious. Okay. I
like to joke, but because it's
Buddhahood is fun. Okay. Okay. You think
it's going to be serious? You believe
all those statues?
[Music]
Okay. So,
anyway, uh he's watching you all the
time and he is you or she is you. Okay.
That's all. She's watching you all the
time. Future Buddha is watching you all
the time. Okay? And you can ask them for
help and they'll give you help. Okay?
It's not crazy. It's a very very healthy
diamond way meditation.
Okay? What was my warning?
Don't talk too loud. Sometimes people
are actually pooping next door that
somebody said I I walked by. You know
how you hear conversations in the office
and somebody say, "Do you know what Gish
Michael does in the
bathroom?" I'm
like, maybe I talk too
loud.
Okay. Uh, next one. You ready? Next
picture. Yeah. I like this picture. I
found it online. It's probably
illegal. I figure Sappa wouldn't mind.
Uh but he has a beautiful
um the next verse he bows down to his
high and holy llama and he does not
mention uh Jetsa. Okay. Chon Lama does
not mention Jets. Chin Lama lived like
200 years after Taba or more actually.
So here's the verse. With the excellent
insight of your incredible
mind, you offered extraordinary
commentary upon the profound, something
that others found difficult to fathom.
Your
purest deeds shone forth with light
above all and known to
everyone. I bow to you in deep respect
at the precious feet of my holy lama.
Okay. Yeah. He has hidden Sappa's name
in the verse. Okay. So, Gibson and me,
we put italics. When you read it in your
book, you you can see to some of the
words are
italicized. That's to alert you that
Chon Lama is having a joke on you.
It looks like he's just bowing down to
some nice person, but he's bowing down
to Sonappa. He has hidden Sonappa's name
in the poetry. And that's a traditional
uh game that great sutra writers, they
play like that. They hide people's names
in the sutra. Okay. Uh sometimes people
ruin the game. They take a knife and
they carve a X under the letter on the
wood block.
So sometimes you'll see a little X under
the under the word in the wood block and
somebody was ruining the
surprise. Okay. But you'll see it. It's
very unusual.
Cool. So there's an idea here that I
wanted to talk
about. I stop at what time? Five punch
bi. Okay. Five o'clock. Okay.
Um, so, so I'm getting older. I I I've
been spending the last few weeks after I
leave here at Diamond Mountain, I have
to leave on time because I start uh
three and a half days of tests uh to get
a new kidney
uh maybe in six years or 10 years or
something like that. So, no, it's not a
good thing. It's like terrible. And uh
it's not yet. Okay. But but you have to
get on the list. To get on the list,
they have to make sure you don't have
cancer. And they don't want to waste a
kidney on you. So uh I have to go for
three and a half days of uh testing and
uh that's so I have to leave on time. It
starts right. I I just barely will make
it. And then I have to sit there for
three days, three and a half days.
They're going to do they're going to
make sure I won't cheat them out of a
kid a good kidney. So I think about I'm
at the age and I guess me Ally people
are we're John we're at the age where
you seriously consider Rob just had a
very dangerous successful operation and
he's promised to live another hundred
years and uh I'm glad for that.
[Applause]
He had triple bypass heart surgery and
then he came to the diamond board
diamond mountain board meeting like 10
days later. He's crazy. But um anyway,
uh so we're aware of uh we I think we're
aware of
uh of the world blacking out. You see
what I mean? this world will black out.
We'll go somewhere else, you know. This
world will just become dark. We'll we'll
see our famil family's faces and then
then everything will be dark for a while
and and then uh we go somewhere else.
But during that dark
moment, try to imagine this word this
world try to imagine this world
uh with no sun and no moon. Okay? Just
it's okay. We have
flashlights. We got cell phones.
Everybody's walking around with a cell
phone. Oh, hi. I didn't see you. You
know, you know, just imagine if the
world
was dark 24 hours a day. Okay, we we
live in a weird world. They
the this week they
uh they found with a spectrome
spectrometer on a satellite that another
planet has two of the chemicals
necessary for
life and they there was a discussion of
whether it's an old fart from somebody
else. It's funny I'm not kidding. You
think I'm kidding.
Uh but this kind of planet is very rare.
We haven't found one for sure yet. Out
of billions of planets, we haven't found
one for sure. We certainly never been
visited for sure. So,
imagine a
planet which is all black. When you get
to our age and you're having these
exotic operations, um it's no joke. You
can imagine the world all black. You
see, all blacked out. Okay, imagine
that. uh if this
world did not have the books that John
Brady is
saving whether there's a sun or a moon
or not it would be in darkness okay try
to think like that imagine that okay you
know why is John so
crazy why are we spending so much work
for 37 years to to save these books you
know why did Gibson spend all I
translating go to India. Somebody
introduced me at a talk in
uh Ecuador or something. They said this
is Gishi
Michael. He he's a gishi and he paid for
it with countless
diarrhea. And I'm
like I said that's the first time anyone
introduced me cor
correctly.
Cuz when you go to those countries in a
refugee camp, you drink one glass of
water, you got diarrhea for three days.
We drank out of a dirty uh stream. We
And I They gave me the water. It was
brown. And they said, "Drink." And I
said, "No, no, get me some bottled
water. We don't have
that." I said, "Get me I'll take water
out of the tap." That is the water out
of the tap, you know. And I said, "Well,
it's gonna give me diarrhea." And they
said, "Yeah, it'll take about a couple
hours." I said, "How long will it last?"
They said, "How long are you
staying?" Anyway,
uh imagine the world without those
books. And and you you don't believe me.
You don't really feel it like like like
I do. But if if those if this little
book by Gibson wasn't didn't exist,
there would be no sun in this world. And
I don't care if there's a physical sun
or there's not a physical sun. That
doesn't matter. The world would be dark.
Okay? You would be stuck with Brad Pitt
movies, Jason
Borne, football games. Don't ask me
which
kind. Okay.
Right. British or American. The British
is not European is not football. I don't
care about Latin America. Okay.
Uh Juan's
like, "Okay. Anyway, imagine the whole
world dark and no stars, no moon, and
and
without without what we're talking about
here, the world would be like that."
Okay. No son ever. Okay. It's like that.
Okay. If these books get lost, if you
don't teach your own students,
uh the the world will be dark.
Okay. Oh, G. I don't want to
go H and teaching out
there in front of all those people. No,
come on. I started in the back of a
Volkswagen. Okay. You got to teach
somebody. Teach your teach your parents.
They'll listen to
you. Okay. All
[Music]
right. Next
picture. I asked the AI to to put a
woman making a Okay, she's got four
fingers.
Someone told me that
uh someone told me that all the artists
in the world put a bug in all the
AIs to always make four fingers and that
way you know it wasn't done by a human
artist. Uh, so I'm sorry. I tried like a
hundred times to put her hand we we say
a promise, right? And the my AI doesn't
let me make dirty pictures. So they're
like some lady going like this is not
appropriate. And I'm no she's making a
promise. So anyway, that's the best I
could do.
This picture refers to uh Chony Lama's
promise to compose this book. Okay. He
promises to explain the verses of Jaton
Kapa. Okay. And the the verses are
short. The verses are cryptic. They are
not obvious. They're kind of secret.
Okay. So, you need an explanation. And
Tony L, we we are using Tony Lama's
explanation. Okay. Um, but there's a
deeper meaning here that's worth $300.
Okay? There's a deeper meaning to
this action in the picture
and it you have to think. You don't just
I have friends who raise their hand just
before I ask the
question and then they they say, "Well,
there's a 50-50 chance I know answer. I
can make some money, you know, because
Gisha doesn't charge for a wrong answer
yet. Yeah. Uh, okay.
$300. Why would this picture Am I going
to make it easy? No. The answer is he
made a pledge to write the work and then
if you do what he says to do, you're
going to get a result if you follow the
steps.
That's not you quite okay. But you're
you're close. $50.
Here, take it.
Wait, they're pointing to each other.
Anybody else?
That looks like a Gbox.
Um the se open to me at this moment that
the picture show the four fingers in the
heart remind me that using four steps
always in the heart.
[Applause]
No, Miss Miss Wind said using the four
steps right all all day in your heart
uh will make you successful.
Now listen Miss
Win a some things in the world cannot be
diamond way
messages right I mean it's ridiculous to
think that an
AI could be delivering tantric
messages right
yeah no
Good. Now, sometimes someone gives
a $1,000 answer to a $300
[Applause]
Sometimes somebody gives a $1,000 answer
to a $300
question. If someone underperforms, you
should
underpay. If someone overperforms, you
should overpay. That's just basic
management. Okay.
Um, anyway, what I was thinking of when
I made the picture,
uh, is that, uh, I think there's a
special message here. And by the way, if
you're in Diamond Way course and you go
around talking about special messages,
uh, you're doing good. That's fine.
Usually, I get irritated if some, oh, I
saw a message. What? The car passed me
on the street. I'm like,
I mean, some people seem to go a little
far, but anyway,
uh it's not bad in a diamond way course.
Okay, every message is a message, even
if it wasn't supposed to be a message.
Okay. Um if they are kind and if they
are based in
morality and that's the answer I
wanted. Okay, he's he's the first act in
Tony Lama's book before he gets to the
first line is to make a promise and he
keeps it. Okay, I I I'll tell you a
beautiful story.
So the only copy of the
congre sutras and tantras uh from India
that still survive and that's all that
survives.
[Music]
Um all the books that Jen Huang are
sutras are included in the kong ting.
Okay. Uh the only copy is in the temple
in New Jersey. Okay. And u somebody
wanted to microfilm it microf fish it uh
because they didn't have computers.
Okay. Then uh my mama
agreed and uh and so you have to
understand it's a
100,000 pages. Okay, it's a 100,000
pages. And he said, "Mike, uh, go get
the first volume and count the
pages and then give them to send them to
the imaging lab and then when it comes
back, count them and make sure they're
all there, right? You
understand?" So, I counted them 200,000
times the pages. This is the kind of
thing I had to do. You don't even know.
I paid for the Gishi degree. Anyway,
um what I'm saying is uh I was I was,
you know, sneaking looks at the content
while I was counting and then I found a
book and it the line was only half
carved, you know, and I was like, that's
weird. And half the line is empty. And
and I I I took the page. I thought my
teacher's, you know, I was always trying
to prove something to my teacher and I
always was finding out I was
wrong. And I went ran to him with the
sheet, you know, it's big page and I
said, "Look, look, there's a half a line
missing." And he says, "Oh my god." And
he read it and he goes and he goes,
"Nope, it's not missing." And I'm like,
"It's missing. There's no no words
there." He said, "Listen, Mike, the guy
died. the author died you know and
that's the only conditions under which
you don't keep your promise to finish
your book is if you die and if you die
halfway through they carve it anyway how
much you finish they carve it's very
unbelievable Dharmakerti did something
like that so okay you it's a serious
promise when you promise to study
diamond weight
course you know it's not a easy thing.
You can't I mean, you can leave halfway
through,
but you know, I'm not saying you're
going to the hell realms. I'm not saying
that,
okay? I And I'm not threatening you. I
don't like that kind of stuff. I think
you're just going to have to sit and
watch TV for 25 lifetimes or some
something terrible like that. Uh
anyway, what this author is saying by
making a promise just before he starts
the Diamond Way explanation of Lam Rim,
what he's saying is you have to keep
your
promises and and keeping your
promises. Basic morality is the
foundation of the diamond way. Okay,
those 10 boring rules, don't kill
Don't steal. Don't mess around with
other people's wives or husbands like
that. Those
10 are the foundation of diamond way.
Okay? And and you can't do diamond way
without that. Okay? So he takes a
promise at the beginning to to show you
how to act. Okay? Got it? Keep your 10
good deeds. Then you can study diamond
way. Okay? Got it? It's a message.
That's a message. It's also there's then
the AI message is separate from Tony
Llama's message.
[Music]
Okay. By the way, I don't have that much
money. So, don't answer any more
questions. I'm kidding. I'm kidding.
Just
kidding.
Okay. How much time you got? Okay.
I'm supposed to start the sales pitches
today. They give you two days rest and
then they start asking you for
donations. I'm I'm the expert. Okay.
Uh were you doing that meditation,
Brian? No. Okay. Just kidding. Just
kidding. Just kidding. Okay. Uh, next
picture. By the way, this carving comes
from one of the 100 volumes in the
Mongolian temple. Okay, they have 101
volumes there. They have one volume of
the 8,000 verses that was carved
separately. They were going to carve the
Kong and Tenure. They finished the
Kongir and then the printing press was
blown up in the cultural revolution.
Okay. They never finished the tinder. Uh
but this one book survived. And
um this is Mangushri. Who's gonna read
the
caption? Mr. Word.
There's a reason why your parents called
you word, right?
Loudly.
Hello. Hello.
Um Gelkun. Yeah. Yes. Okay. Good.
Um, say sa. Oh, okay. Oh, okay. Um, sen.
Yeah. Um, Jang.
Yeah. Good. Jang. Okay. Jang or Jang.
Okay. Yeah.
Uh so it's manushri and jambbeang means
jam jamba means
uh soft like
velvet. It's very soft to like silk and
uh yang means a song. Okay. So mjush mju
means soft and kosha means song. And so
you can call
mju or you can call mju gosha same
thing. Okay. And he bows
down. Now we're starting with Jets
Kappa is making his own promise to write
his book because the last promise we saw
was by Tony Lama. So if you're not
careful, you'll say why why did Gibson
put an extra promise in there? Where is
Gibson? I got to pick on you. Hi. Uh
yeah. So there's two promises in a The
second promise is by Saba and he bows
down to his own teacher which is uh
Manushri. Okay. Manushri. Uh then I I
had trouble with Mushouchri. I remember
uh when I asked my
teacher you know what's the story with
Mushouchri you know and he says he's a
Buddha. And then I'm like okay there's
more than one Buddha. And he's like,
"Yeah, there's zillions of Buddhists."
And I'm like, "Well, why they have an
extra one?" And then because I just came
from Princeton. I don't know anything.
And and he's like, "Yeah, there's an
extra Buddha called Mandushri." And I'm
like, "Well, why is there an extra
Buddha? Isn't Shakyamuni enough?" You
know, and they're like, "Well, he's the
Buddha wisdom, you know." I'm like, "Is
Shakyamuni doesn't have wisdom?
And he's like, "Just shut
up." That was later he later I got
confused. My name is Mike or just shut
up. Uh so anyway, uh yeah, Mjushi
represents
uh the understanding of emptiness. Okay.
If you if you learn what Manushri can
teach, you will you will touch the
diamond world. Okay. And some of you
know from DCI, you know the story. So
there was
a sheep
herder wandering around the mountains in
Tibet and his name was Umapa which
happens to mean middleway by accident
and uh he's just taking care of
sheep and then uh Jets Kappa was having
trouble understanding emptiness and he
asked
people is there anyone who really
understands emptiness alive and they by
the way the situation in Tibet at that
time was the same as America or the west
now there wasn't enough people who
understood anything about
Buddhism there was very few people so he
said is there anyone who really
understands emptiness and they said yeah
Lama
Umapa and he says well which monastery
is he in they said he's not any
monastery he's a
sheer is he monk
No. Well, how can he understand about
emptiness? Just go talk to him. You
know, he he can talk to Mushouchi
directly. He has a direct cell phone to
uh you know
Verizon. What do you call Buddha
Verizon? Anyway, he can talk to
the he can talk to Mushouch. So, there's
a beautiful story. And Sonappa climbed
around the mountains, found the best
sheep hurting pastures, found Lama
Umapa, who was a very
quiet,
respectful, you know, person just
walking around with sheep. And he and he
said, "Are you a mama?" And he's like,
"Yes." And he said, "Can you talk to
Mjushi?" And he said, "Yes."
And he said, so Grab was
like, I'll be honest, I don't believe
you. You know, and Umab is like, do you
think I care? You
know, and then that's that's how it
goes. And then
uh and so Kappa says, "I'm going to test
you, you know." And um Mapa's like,
"Yeah, okay." You know, wait, I got to
go catch this sheep. I'll be back. you
know, he's like, "Okay, test me." And
so, Sappa thought about the most
difficult ideas of emptiness, deep
questions, you know, like how can a
cause make a result if they never touch
each
other? And if they don't touch each
other, why does why doesn't the cause
cause all results? Because it doesn't
touch everything else also.
And if you say they do touch, then they
have to exist at the same
time. And if the cause exists at the
same time as the result, it cannot be
the cause for the
result. You know, he's asking him stuff
like
that. Then he really wanted to know and
then Umaba gave him answers and they
were perfect. They were, you know,
Tonkaba was like, "Oh my gosh, I never
realized that." You know he gave
beautiful answers. The the cause and the
result are the cause is not causing the
result. You see the cause causing the
result. You see the
pen making
writing because your seeds according to
Miss
Win create the pen and then they create
the writing. It's not the pen creating
the writing but the pen comes before the
writing. Got it?
That's real cause and effect. And so was
like, "Oh my god, I never understood
that." You know, and he was blown away.
Okay. So after a while, he got
irritated, I think, climbing up in all
through the sheep poop. And uh he said
he asked a better question. This is
those three wishes
question. There's a good joke about
that, but I can only tell the boys.
Um later
uh he said I should have asked you the
best question of all which is what
yeah how do you talk to Majushi directly
you know and then Majushi is like you're
supposed to be so smart but you didn't
ask me that before and he taught him how
to talk to him directly and so when
sonapa bows down to Manushri
uh he bowed bows down. When he bows down
to his teacher, he bows down to Manushri
because he was his
teacher and he could see Mandushi. He
could ask Manushi questions. Okay. Then
um diamond
way in diamond way
uh we would say Tonkapa was
Manushi. Okay. in sutra way
non-tandantra sutra way
uh you could say that uh sonapa made
contact
with mushri right you you could say that
or something like that and then sapa's
students said but he is majushi he's not
majushi
student he is majushi you know so then
this those students had diamond weight
teachings. They they understood the
diamond weight. They understood he
wasn't a student of Mushu. He was Mushu.
Okay, got
it. So throughout history, many people
have not recognized who's the real
teacher here. You see what I mean? uh
they said Tonkapa was studying with
Manushri and then those who understood
diamond way
uh said that Sonappa was
Mushri and then those who studied
diamond mountain
diamond they say something different for
$100 don't raise your
Man, don't let everybody else make the
money.
Gila is majushi.
I'm not. I I swear I'm
not. I
wish. I'm working on it.
[Music]
Okay. Yeah.
It's not that he
is the emanation of Manu.
Okay. So we can say you know he had to
talk to the sheep herder to talk to
Manushri first level. Second level he
was man m man m man m man m man m man m
man m man m man m man m manushri right
and then third level in diamond
mountain.
Okay, cancel the bet. Anybody want to
try car? Okay, come on. Come on.
I don't want a long sentence. I don't
want all the Harry Potter books. I I
want one short sentence. It's not that
he for sure and it's not that he is
uh It's not that he is for sure and it's
it's not that he's not for sure.
[Music]
That's a $100 answer.
Anyway, no you are mushri. You are
mushri. Okay, you are mushri. Okay, it's
one thing to pray to
mushri. It's another thing to realize
your teacher is manushri. But the goal
of this class is to realize who you are.
You are mushri.
That's the goal of diamond mountain
diamond ray. Okay, that's real diamond
ray. Okay, understand you are mushri. If
you
didn't you didn't know it yet. Okay, the
whole diamond away course is going to
uh clean away the dirt on the mirror and
then you'll say, "Oh my
god, it looks very similar to me."
Okay. Got it. Okay. All right.